[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer org
slash software are you tech savvy
developer with an inquisitive mind SC
radio has an opening for a new volunteer
host to join the team and produce five
episodes per year
contact show host Robert bloomin at
Robert bloomin at BL um en at gmail.com
for details for sovereign Janeane radio
this is Elena Salinas today's episode is
about machine learning with Katy Malone
who is a data scientist in the research
and development department at civis
analytics katie has a PhD in physics
from Stanford University and her
background is in particle physics she
worked on searching for new particles at
CERN in Switzerland which involves data
science and machine learning
katie is also an instructor of the intro
to machine learning online course from
Udacity which I personally really liked
and she's also host of linear
digressions a podcast that explores
machine learning and data science
through interesting and sometimes
unusual applications Katy Malone
welcome to software engineering radio
well thank you so much for having me I'm
delighted to be here machine learning is
widely use we see it in search engines
speech recognition language translation
now we see it in our Netflix
recommendations and most recently in
driverless cars in the coming years
we're going to start seeing it being
used in more fields
first I want to begin by defining what
machine learning is what is machine
learning so let me take a step back and
answer it this way which is that my
background is in science and so I have
this kind of innate belief that there's
truth in the world and that science is
one of the ways that we can understand
that truth that we can get it out of the
world around us and it's really it's
really hard to measure truth directly
but one of the things that we can do
instead is collect data on the world and
then if we analyze that data then
sometimes we can pull out the truth that
way so a truth a true thing about the
world might be something like I'm
interested in watching this movie or it
might be something like there's a good
way to translate this sentence that I
just said from English to French and the
thing about machine learning is machine
learning is in my view a suite of tools
that allows you to analyze that data and
figure out you know what's actually
going on in the world and how that's
expressed in the data so usually it
involves pretty heavy computational
lifting obviously machine learning is
that the machine component of it is
implying computers and then there's also
usually a heavy dose of statistics and
very often additional scientific fields
as well so if you're trying to study
something like human behavior then
there's a whole suite of things that you
should be aware of about the way that
humans you know behave in the world and
things like behavioral psychology and
economics and sort of all those other
things that give you context about how
to study you know the thing that you're
interested in studying so what you're
mentioning is machine learning can be
about measuring the truth through
collecting data and analyzing this data
how does this relate to the field of
artificial intelligence oh that's an
interesting question I once heard a good
description of artificial intelligence
and the distinction between machine
learning and artificial intelligence I
think it's a little bit of a false
distinction but the idea is that machine
learning focuses more on understanding
that truth trying to
Stan what's going on in the world or to
measure what's going on or to make
predictions perhaps and artificial
intelligence is a little bit more
thinking one step further once we have
those predictions or we understand
what's going on how can we make better
decisions or we can change you know the
way that we do things in the future so
as to like take advantage of those
insights that we've gained so artificial
intelligence sort of builds upon machine
learning and I feel like it is kind of
adding that layer of decision-making or
changing the way that you do things as a
result of machine learning let's walk
through a simple example of machine
learning one that I see all the time is
in email clients like Gmail when I get
an email there's a button to win de Kate
if an email is spam let's talk about
what can happen under the hood in a spam
detection system once I indicate that an
email is spam I am telling the system
showing the system something what can
machine learning do with that
information in order to start building a
model about what spam is yeah sure so
email is a really good example of a case
of what we would call probably
supervised classification so there's two
parts of that let me break that apart
supervised the idea of supervision and
machine learning is the idea that
somehow you have the correct answer for
some of the cases so in this case the
correct answer is you manually labeling
an email and telling it that it's spam
and kind of implicitly if you don't tell
it that it's spam
then it assumes that it's a legitimate
email and that may or may not be a
correct assumption but let's assume that
most of the time you know the labels so
to speak of these emails then end up
being reflective of what the emails
actually are and then classification is
the idea of we're trying to sort things
into two buckets is it spammers and not
spam and so the idea of machine learning
is that based on the attributes of the
email we can make predictions we can
learn what a spammy email looks like and
we can extrapolate those patterns onto
new emails that we don't know whether
they're spam or not and we can make a
good prediction so in the case of
something like
what looks like a spamming email it's
probably going to look at the words in
the email potentially also the domain
that the email is coming from but
especially especially for emails spam
has very particular patterns of like the
words that they actually use in spam
tend to be pretty distinctive like
they're usually trying to sell you
something there's usually lots of
superlative adjectives about how great
it is or maybe they're trying to get you
to send money to somebody in some
foreign country very often there's
grammatical mistakes so that based on
the presence of particular words
Nigerian prince or whatever um then it
can you know from all these supervised
cases that you've given it where you've
said that this is spam it can basically
learn those patterns and then apply
those patterns to new cases and
hopefully then at some point you don't
have to manually label anymore emails
it's just figured out what spam looks
like so that we don't need another
human-in-the-loop to indicate a certain
word as spam the system is able to
figure out those common words their
currencies yeah I think well so spam is
an interesting case because presumably
spammers are getting more sophisticated
and so the spam filters that might have
worked five years ago probably wouldn't
work that well right now so that is
another aspect of machine learning
that's pretty important it's it very
often it's pretty rare to have a problem
that you solved once and for all with
machine learning usually you want to go
back and revisit it periodically and see
if the solutions you came up with last
year or last month they're still
applying so spam is a good example of I
don't know if people talk about Nigerian
Prince's anymore because that's just
such a cliche at this point but the
basic formula of we're gonna pretend
that there's some amount of money that's
sitting in an account somewhere and you
just have to send us some small deposit
and we'll release it to you the exact
details of that might change and so then
you have to keep retraining your machine
learning algorithm to sort of continue
to to make good decisions in that
scenario and two of the things that you
mentioned of characteristics of an email
is the first one was the words certain
words that occur and the other one is
the domain how is this information
represented is there a specific format
for this oh yeah the machine learning
model yeah that's that's a really good
question and it's very important so in
this particular case usually with
something like text classification the
simplest thing that you can do is you
can treat each word as its own type of
feature so a lot of these machine
learning algorithms under the hood they
assume that there's big matrices of
attributes so imagine a matrix is kind
of a big data table and each row in that
table is an email in this case and each
column in that in that matrix is a word
and so if there's a particular word that
shows up in a particular email then
you'll get probably a one-in in that
spot in the matrix and if it doesn't
show up then there's a zero so then with
this big matrix which is gonna be mostly
zeros we'll call it a it's often called
a sparse matrix because it's mostly
zeros it's there's very few ones with
that matrix representation then you can
put that into you know some of your
standard machine learning algorithms and
and it can figure out then how to to
find the structure in that matrix that
allows it to understand which words are
most closely associated with the emails
that you classify to spam so you
mentioned the sparse matrix is there an
impact in the fact that there are a lot
of zeros in this data structure oh
that's a really good question and in
general yes
so some algorithms depending on exactly
what type of algorithm you're using that
can be no problem at all or it can be a
big concern and so one of the other
important aspects of machine learning is
sometimes thinking about different
representations of your data so the way
that I described it is just the simplest
way that you might represent the data in
an email but there's other algorithms
that can be a little bit more compressed
with respect to how it you know
represents the the types of words or the
types of sentences that are showing up
in an email and so those types of
decisions about how you're going to
represent your data have a pretty
intimate connection with the type of
algorithm that you're actually
to use to to do the pattern recognition
so to speak the actual supervised
classification algorithm and so yeah it
makes a huge difference and this is a
place where people spend a lot of time
and effort is thinking about the best
ways to represent their data because
this give this gets back very quickly to
the idea of trying to that the data is
representing some kind of latent truth
that we're trying to understand and so
then the way that the that the data is
formatted can make it very easy for us
to like find that truth so to speak or I
can make it you know really hard so it's
worth thinking about pretty carefully
and what is one way in which this data
has been compressed in other data
structures oh sure
so one that I think is pretty
interesting is you you brought up the
issue at the very beginning of Netflix
movie recommendations and that's another
case of where you have a big sparse
matrix so you imagine that each person
who watches movies is a row and each
possible movie that they could watch is
a column and so most people will only
watch one percent of movies or something
like that of all the movies that are out
there and most movies that are out there
are not going to be watched by even a
significant fraction of all the Netflix
users so you have again this kind of big
sparse matrix and so what you can do
with something like Netflix is you can
use what's called matrix factorization
and the rough idea of matrix
factorization is instead of having this
big sparse matrix let's imagine that
there's basically two factors that are
two different types of attributes that
we're trying to understand we're trying
to understand types of users who watch
movies we say that there's like certain
buckets of users or like segments of
users there's let's say families with
kids and those watch certain types of
movies and then there might also be you
know 20 year old guys who really likes
other types of movies and then maybe
there's like middle-aged women who like
a third type of movie or not even just a
single type of movie but like certain
add mixtures of movies so we have kind
of like types of users on the one hand
and then we have analogously types of
movies on the other hand so you might
have action movies or mysteries or
foreign documentaries or
whatever and so whether a particular
user likes a particular movie is kind of
a combination of what type of user they
are and what type of movie it is and so
that's a way they're sort of like this
linear algebra process that you can go
through to try to take this big sparse
matrix and approximate it as basically
the product of two smaller matrices one
that's about your users and one that's
about your movies and so that's a way of
representing that same data in a
different way but in a way that can
sometimes make it a lot more easy and
direct to try to figure out in this case
of a particular user is gonna like a
particular type of movie yeah and this
is so so good I think because it reminds
me of where we talked about earlier
about updating a model what you start
watching as a little kid and then
suddenly you're a teenager then you're
married and your interests keep evolving
and with this way it would be updating
it right because there's different
matrices yeah and one of the other
things that's nice about it is in
recommendation engines there's also this
classic problem of cold starts so let's
say there's a new movie that gets added
to Netflix next month and you know
Netflix is trying to figure out if they
should give it really valuable real
estate on the front page and like
advertise it to people so they're
basically trying to figure out if a lot
of people are gonna want to watch it but
they they have no data on this movie yet
they don't know who's watched it or who
would like it before or they don't have
any information about who has watched it
yet because they haven't put it on their
website
um and so this is kind of a tricky place
to be in terms of machine learning
because you usually machine learning is
about pattern recognition and there's no
pattern there yet but if you have some
other contextual information like we
know that this is an action movie then
you have a little bit of a better place
where you're starting from and you have
some idea of who are the people who like
action movies and so that's a place
where you can be a little bit more
effective especially right at the
beginning and then sort of refine those
estimates as you actually put the movie
out there and you collect more data
about who's watching it and we've been
talking about supervised
machine learning earlier about
classification the spam email putting
the data into buckets spam or not spam
can supervise learning be apply also to
values that are continuous instead of
discrete oh sure yeah so that's usually
called regression and actually a lot of
the same algorithms can be used for
classification and regression and it's
kind of an issue of just flipping back
and forth between the final type of
output that you want so definitely yeah
mm-hmm
what is one example of what you just
mentioned that the algorithms can be
applied to both oh so decision trees are
one type of algorithm that I know that
there's decision tree regression and
there's decision tree classification
okay can you explain a little bit more
regression for example linear regression
what the objective is
oh sure yes so linear regression like
you said has more of a continuous output
and maybe the way to think about this
that's a little bit more useful is where
classification is trying to figure out
if something is a or B spam or not spam
the thing about spam and not spam is
there isn't really a natural ordering of
those two things like you wouldn't say
that spam has an inherently like higher
value than not spam or vice versa but if
you're trying to do something like
predict somebody's income based off of
like other attributes that you can see
about them then obviously there's a
natural ordering if you have one person
that you predict that they make $10,000
a year and there's someone else who
makes $100,000 a year there's a sort of
a natural ordering to them and any
regardless of what amount of money
somebody makes you can put them in this
kind of spectrum that has this natural
ordering to it so what linear regression
tries to do is it says we have a list of
attributes about a certain person and
we're trying to predict their income
we'll just use that example for now so
based on these attributes what do I see
is the relationship between a person's
attribute and their income so one
example might be age and you might say
that the older someone tends to get up
to us
and point at least the more money they
tend to make because they're more
experienced or whatever you might also
say something like I can observe what
kind of car this person drives and I
know that there are certain patterns in
terms of income versus the the type of
transportation that you use basically
the richer people have access to nicer
cars and none of these patterns are
gonna hold
absolutely for every single case that
you can look at but statistically
they'll usually hold and from that you
can make you know sort of predictions
the quality of those predictions will
depend very much on how good your data
is and to a lesser extent how good your
algorithm is but again you're getting a
little bit closer than if you were to
just sort of make a shot in the dark
guess in a way to visualize this is if
we plot for example in one axis the
income and you know another axis that
type of car then not the type of car but
the price of the car - maybe predict
with what income how much you spend in
cars right yeah that would give you some
idea and then you could imagine fitting
like a line to basically that
distribution that you see and the slope
of that line is gonna tell you sort of
how much more you're gonna estimate
about somebody's income once you know
how expensive their car is how do we
measure how good the line is compared to
the data yeah so there's a few standard
metrics that you know kind of everyone
uses so for something like comparing
lines to a data set what you'll very
often use is for every data point that
you have in your data set you'll pick
the prediction that's given to you by
the line
like if something with if someone you
know driving a car of this value there
if I see someone driving a car that has
a certain value what do I predict about
their income and that's gonna be just
where do they fall on this line and then
you'll say for that person where did
what was their actual income and so
let's say for there's somebody who's
driving a really expensive car and so I
think they make $100,000 a year and then
when I actually look at my data set I
find that they make a hundred and ten
thousand dollars a year so that
difference that ten thousand dollars
then usually I'll say that that was my
error or
sometimes you square it for other
reasons that we don't have to get into
and then you sum that up over your whole
data set and you say and probably divide
by the number of points that you had and
you said you know this is a this is a
metric for my goodness of fit of this
line but I think one of the other things
that's interesting about metrics is that
for a lot of machine learning algorithms
there's standard metrics that you can
use so for classification you can use
something like accuracy which is how
many did you get right divided by how
many total cases did you try to classify
but one of the big challenges of machine
learning and data science is trying to
figure out if those metrics are like
really actually measuring the thing that
you care about because usually they
aren't and you have to be a little bit
smarter than just the metrics and figure
out exactly what it is you care about
and then modify the metrics a little bit
to reflect that so you know you usually
have good options but then part of the
artistry is like knowing when to leave
those options behind and we'll talk a
little bit more about evaluation metrics
later on but first I want to shift the
topic a little bit to unsupervised
machine learning we've been talking
about supervised machine learning for
discrete values and for continuous
values how is unsupervised machine
learning different than supervised so
the sort of canonical answer is that for
unsupervised machine in supervised
machine learning you have correct
answers that sort of came to you with
your data set with unsupervised machine
learning you don't have that luxury
you just have data and so usually the
types of questions that you can ask of
that data are kind of different and very
often constrained by the fact that
there's no sort of like correct answer
that you're trying to find and so that
really changes the character of the work
in a lot of ways in my opinion when I've
tried to do unsupervised learning it's
very challenging and it's a really
different way of thinking about your
data because with supervised machine
learning there's basically like a
correct answer and what you want to do
is just try to get as close as possible
to that correct answer with unsupervised
machine learning it can be very tricky
to try to understand what a good answer
looks like so that you would recognize
it when you saw it on
supervised methods would be things like
clustering if you have a data set and
you think there's kind of like groups or
clumps or clusters and that data then
clustering is usually considered an
unsupervised method and also some of
these matrix decomposition or some of
the feature reduction techniques like
principal components analysis is another
if people are familiar with that is
another unsupervised method so again
there's sort of different types of
questions that you might try to answer
with unsupervised learning and it in my
experience is really really hard
what does some of those questions look
like that you've done in the past yeah
so the the biggest one in my experience
that I that I've worked with before has
been clustering and again that's just
sort of the idea that you have you know
these blobs and the data and you and you
want to try to find them that there's
sort of these coherent clumps and that's
hard because with a lot of real-world
datasets you don't really you don't know
if they're clusters in the data set to
begin with you know so if you don't find
any it's really hard to know if that's
because you're doing a bad job or
because it just doesn't exist this gets
back a little bit to the idea of like
truth and like you know what are we what
are we trying to understand here in the
world and then for things like principal
components analysis the idea of
principal components analysis is you're
trying to find sort of like directions
in your data set in a lower dimensional
space again this gets back to the idea
of like feature representation sometimes
directions in your data set in a lower
dimensional space that maximize the
variance in your data so you're trying
to find ways of sort of compressing the
data down to the aspects that make it
like the most variable that's not a
particularly good way of explaining it
but the point is that it's something
that you can do without knowing any sort
of quote-unquote correct answers for
your data so that can be like pretty
useful when you don't have labels to
rely on and we're where we'll be see
this on a regular basis for example for
supervised we talked about the spam
email unsupervised machine learning is
it widely use is there any systems that
we interact with that under the hood
might be using unsupervised machine
learning oh yeah that's a good question
so a lot of
clustering analyses and so this will
sometimes show up in something like
maybe if you work in marketing trying to
think of a segmentation so if you think
that your users might fall into a few
main buckets let's say I'm thinking of
selling a computer and I have my power
users like my programmers and my data
scientists and whatever but then I also
have people who just use it as like an
internet machine and they just watch
movies on it and use Facebook maybe
there's people who use it as a work
machine but they're not programming on
it you know so you could think that
maybe there's a data set that would
somehow allow you to pick out that
there's these distinct groups some of
the other interesting places for
unsupervised methods or off the top of
my head I think there's some really cool
stuff that I've heard about in genomics
so genomics they have this problem where
there's something like three billion
base pairs in the human genome and so
trying to figure out which of those are
actual genes that control you know
things that we might care about like
diseases or you know whether you get
sick eventually whether you have health
problems of all different kinds and so
that can be a really challenging machine
learning problem for a lot of reasons
and so sometimes you have to throw
unsupervised methods at that because
it's not well-defined enough at the
outset what question it is you're trying
to answer and so just trying to like
bring that data problem under control a
little bit sometimes forces you into a
space that's a little bit more
unsupervised
so supervised might also be more about
discoverability because you you don't
necessarily know what you're looking for
yeah I think that's probably fair you
know supervised methods or what you yeah
what you use when you know what it is
you're trying to answer and then
unsupervised methods are for either
where you don't have that labeled data
available or where you don't exactly
know how to slice and dice the data yet
we've mentioned several algorithms for
supervised and unsupervised machine
learning we also talked about some
potential applications of it in one
language are machine learning algorithms
typically written in the the go-to
languages if you're in data science
anyway our R and Python and then I think
there's also implementations that are in
a number of other
languages that just don't have as much
pick up in the community so C++ or Java
or whatever there's you know machine
learning implementations and in a lot of
other languages that you know are
sometimes used in like boutique cases
but I think are in Python or like the
powerhouse languages so Python is the
most popular one I think so I think it
depends a little bit on on how you
define data scientist or machine
learning but I think R and Python are
fairly close I like Python better but
that's just me okay let's talk about the
data in machine learning before choosing
a machine algorithm machine learning
algorithm I've heard that it's important
to look on the data first do you agree
with this yes I think that's incredibly
important I think it's also incredibly
hard sometimes
so I'll just say that at the outset but
things like missing data things like
biases in your data things like mistakes
and outliers and things like that those
can really mess up a machine learning
algorithm and the fastest way to get a
handle on a data set is just by looking
at it
and for example if you're inspecting a
large data set you would just pick a
subset of it right
randomly or yeah I guess it depends on
how big I mean if you can look at the
whole data set then you know by all
means look at the whole thing but yeah
if you're working with big enough data
sets yeah you'll probably have to like
randomly subset it okay another common
term when talking about data and machine
learning is cleaning the data and
transforming the data yeah what does
this mean what does this encompass that
is an excellent question and I will name
some things but invariably you know
there's always there's always corner
cases that don't get covered by the
stuff that you think you need to do so a
few examples are looking for outliers so
data points that are just far far
outside of the general distribution and
this can either be because they're truly
interesting and anomalous events like
you managed to just find bill gates and
you're in your data set or something and
Bill Gates just is a very different
person than the rest of the world in a
lot of ways
or what's more likely is that there's a
mistake in the data and that somebody
you know hit an extra nine when they're
entering somebody's income and it's just
a it's just an error so those are things
that you would then want to clean up
very often you can also have missing
data and so then you have to figure out
what you want to do in those cases most
machine learning algorithms don't
particularly handle it well if you have
missing data there's all kinds of things
you can do to deal with that that'll
have different implications downstream
for the answers that you get yeah I
think that it's really hard to know in
advance what kind of shape data is going
to be in and how much work it's going to
be to clean it like it's one of those
things that you really only start to
know how messy a dataset is once you get
your hands on it but it's hugely
important yeah that's a really good
point and it's something that I would
say most I mean the other thing is I'm
even getting ahead of myself here a lot
of times data doesn't come in in like a
nice matrix format where you have you
know rows and columns it comes in in
some mess and you have to figure out how
to format it before you can even start
to think about visualizing it and you
know maybe there's a whole bunch of
tables that you need to join together
and it's all complicated that way too so
yeah it can actually end up being a huge
part of your work as a data scientist
which is kind of too bad because it's
not particularly fun but whoever figures
out a good way to reliably automate this
is gonna make a billion dollars and more
power to them because our lives are all
going to be our lives in the you know
machine learning and data science
community anyway yeah well I'll benefit
from it yeah do current tools for
example Python alleviates some of this
for example in finding outliers yeah
yeah there's certainly methods that you
can bring to bear on this the thing
that's hardest just knowing what kind of
messy data problem you have and how to
fix it so what yeah a lot of problems
are as soon as you figure out the right
way to like slice and dice the data that
you can see it it's immediately obvious
what the problem is it's just that
usually figuring out how to slice and
dice the data to understand what's going
on that's the hard part is just figuring
out what your problem is
I wonder if machine learning can be
applied to that like to all the cleaning
before and after data sets
personally deeply hope so like I think
that there's stuff that you can the
thing that's tricky about it is I think
you can get probably 80% of the way
there with a lot of with a lot of tools
that are already on the market it's just
like knowing how to put them together
for a particular data set and the thing
about it is that even if you get 80% of
the way there that last 20% can still
really mess you up so I think a lot of
data sign as much as we would love to
have automated cleaning tools I think
there would also be a lot of skepticism
of them in the data science community I
think data scientists would still we I
would still tell people to look at their
to look at their data make sure you
understand it even if you have the best
cleaning tool in the world I don't think
there's such a thing as a as a perfect
cleaning tool
one more thing related to data is for
supervised algorithms like we discussed
earlier we provide label data when
building the machine learning model what
does it mean the training data and the
testing data oh sure yeah this is a
really good point so the idea is you
have some big data set that you are
starting with so when we say training a
machine learning algorithm it's
basically giving it a set of labeled
examples and having it use those to
figure out what the patterns are but the
thing about it is that then the next
question you want to ask is how good is
this algorithm that I've just made how
good is it going to be at predicting
labels for new cases that it hasn't seen
yet and the way you need to answer that
question is you need to give it new
cases that it hasn't seen yet but for
which you actually know the correct
answer so you can see if it gets it
right or not and so that's what your
test data set is for and it's really
important that you separate your
training data from your test data before
you start doing any machine learning
because it's really easy for machine
learning algorithms to basically just
memorize their training data which is
not a particularly good position to be
in because it means that they're all
they know is what they've memorized they
haven't figured out how to like extend
it to new cases and then the other
problem is that then if you give it an
example that it's already seen before
and you say do you know the answer to
this then it will tell you
yes of course it'll give you the right
answer but that doesn't necessarily mean
that it would get the right answer in a
similar case in the future like again
it's sort of this problem where it's
just memorize the answer it hasn't
really like learned anything so it's
really important that you not be fooled
by that particular mistake and that's
what your test data is for that you have
to keep it partitioned off from your
training data and you only use it to try
to understand the performance of your
algorithm on new cases that it hasn't
seen before what is the process for
determining what percentage of the data
we should use for training and what
percentage for testing yeah different
people will give you different answers
for this and it can depend on it can
depend on sort of how much data you have
overall and like how high the
dimensionality is and stuff like that
one of the things that is a little bit
nicer than just training and testing as
I describe it now is what's Col called
k-fold cross-validation or sometimes
it's called n fold cross validation and
so the idea is imagine you had you you
have your data set and let's say it's a
three fold cross validation that you're
running so in that case what you'll do
is you'll split your data into three
equal parts just randomly you train on
2/3 and then you test on the third piece
and then you do that again but you train
on you know instead of train on a and B
and test on C you train on B and C and
you test on a and so then you can do
that you know three times in total and
so then every every example that you
have ends up using being used for both
training and testing so it's it's a way
that you can get like a little bit more
juice out of your data so that's
actually probably the preferred way to
do evaluation is actually using k-fold
cross-validation and it's also important
that the data is randomized right
yes that's usually important there are
so many times that I've gotten very
confused by having a data set that isn't
randomized so by not randomized I mean
like imagine our spam case but all of
our spam emails are like in the first
you know hundred rows and then
everything after that is not spam it's
really easy to get an algorithm that
doesn't do very well because you're
basically training it on one type of
data and then test
another type of data and of course I
wouldn't do well why would it why would
it know what not spam looks like it only
knows what spam looks like so if you
randomize your data at the outset then
it should solve this problem but it's
just one of those like classic things
that every time I do it I get very
confused for about a half hour and then
I or well hopefully less at this point
I'm a little bit smarter but you know it
used to be I would be just scratching my
head for 45 minutes trying to figure out
what's going on and then and then you
figure it out and you kind of just smack
yourself on the head and then it's
really easy to fix but well it's very
confusing when that happens to you you
know is this do you randomized using
Python so in Python what I'm usually
using for machine learning is
scikit-learn which is just a library for
machine learning and then in the
scikit-learn k-fold cross-validation and
also in all of their cross validation
stuff I think they have randomization
flags that you can set that'll just like
shuffle everything so I don't have to do
it manually anymore although that was
what I used to do yeah yeah yeah because
that's what I was wondering I'm like it
should just be a requirement but a flag
makes sense yeah I think I think it's a
I think it's a flag at this point yes
let's talk now a little bit more on
evaluation metrics you mentioned earlier
accuracy and that you don't always want
to go by the accuracy why is that why is
accuracy not sufficient yeah it's a
really good question there are a few
different answers that I'm that I might
give so just a couple off the top of my
head one is imagine that you have a data
set that's very imbalanced so let's
suppose that the vast majority of the
email that you get is actually
legitimate email and there's only let's
say 10% of it is spam and so then if
what you're doing is it's really easy in
those circumstances for machine learning
algorithms to you know the heuristic
that they learn is just always classify
it as not spam and so it's not your
machine learning algorithm isn't really
actually doing anything in that case but
if you're relying on accuracy to tell
you if you have a good algorithm or not
then it's gonna say even though your
your algorithm basically isn't doing
it's still getting it right 90% of the
time and so then that 90% accuracy
metric might fool you into thinking that
you have a really great classifier when
you have you know you're very far from
that
another thing about accuracy is that it
treats all kinds of errors and all kinds
of successes as like basically equal so
let's imagine that what we have is some
tract some kind of classifier that's
trying to tell if you have a very
serious disease and let's suppose that
this disease is you know if you catch it
early then treatment is like fairly
straightforward and things like that but
if you don't catch it then it can be
like a gigantic problem and so maybe in
that case it's more expensive for you to
make the mistake of missing a case of
this disease than it is for you to like
accidentally flag someone as having it
and and asking them to come in for more
testing because let's say the you know
the further testing would just verify
that that they were actually okay and
they didn't need to do anything so
there's kind of different costs that are
associated with the different types of
mistakes you might make accuracy by
itself won't reflect that and so you
might end up in this case where you know
you think that it's equally harmful to
like make both of those kinds of
mistakes but in real life that might not
be the case and what you mean in the
medical example is that you also want to
you don't want to ignore people that
were detected to have the disease but
they turn out to not have it you want to
evaluate whoever turned positive right
yeah so so in that case I guess what I'm
imagining is that you know it's not that
expensive for us to accidentally have a
false positive to accidentally think
that someone has this disease when they
don't like let's say that the treatment
is they have to take extra vitamins and
so maybe that's not that big of a deal
if you if you don't have the disease
like taking extra vitamins you have to
pay a little bit of money and that that
might not be great but like it's not a
big problem but if you're one of the
people who actually did have the disease
you don't get diagnosed and so you're
not able to take the vitamins you know
and so you might get really sick and
that's actually a huge problem so in
this case we would probably want to
err on the side of you know
over-diagnosing a little bit in this
particular case that even if we aren't
exactly sure if we think there's like
even a kind of slight chance that
someone might have this disease I just
go ahead and prescribe the just go ahead
and prescribe the vitamins like that's
the kind of mistake that we would prefer
to make and so accuracy is gonna treat
both of those kinds of mistakes that's
equally bad when in fact they're not
what are the what is the name of this
this other metric for evaluating one is
accuracy but how do you call the the one
where you're also considering false
positives oh yeah so there's there's a
few different ones depending on exactly
what parts of it you care about the most
so there's precision and that's that's
the idea for people who I flag is having
this disease how often am I actually
correct about it there's recall which
says that of everyone who gets tested
how often do I actually detect it when
somebody has the disease and then
there's different add mixtures so
there's what's called the receiver
operator characteristic curve which is a
little bit more sophisticated and so
that's trying to look at like both the
true positive rate and the false
positive rate at the same time there's
what's called the F score which is a
combination of precision and recall and
then if you actually if you can do it
the thing that's best is to attach types
of costs to each of the mistakes that
you might make and this might be really
hard for most cases but you know let's
say that you have an easier example of
like you're trying to sell products and
you're just figuring out who to market
products to like you probably know
approximately how expensive it is to
like advertise to one more person you
probably know how much money you expect
to make if you manage to successfully
advertise to them and they buy your
product so then what you're trying to do
is just do this sort of like
cost-benefit trade off and you're gonna
pick the point that just maximizes how
much money you make so that's gonna be
some combination of how much money you
make because there because people are
buying your product and then there's
gonna be the money that you lose because
you have to advertise the people and
that cost money and so just finding and
like kind of the maximum on that curve
is probably what you want to do and like
you said choosing an evaluation metric
and
depend on the type of problem that we're
dealing with right medical is not
necessarily the same as you said
marketing yeah for sure and like are you
trying to do classification of just
people into you know different buckets
or one of the things that comes up in
medicine a lot as you're trying to
assess the risk of something happening
to a person within you know let's say
the risk of them getting heart disease
in the next five years or something like
that and so that you know getting that
risk score correct having that be an
accurate probability basically of what
the actual risk is for them you know
that's a slightly different question and
you're gonna use slightly different
metrics to figure out if your model is
doing a good job if that's what you want
out is an accurate probability instead
of like an accurate label so there's
yeah there's all kinds of different
scenarios depending on exactly what it
is you're studying and what it is you're
trying to measure last question and I
want to talk about machine learning as a
career or data science
what does someone that work in this
field feel do on a regular basis at a
higher level so yeah a lot of it is is
the cleaning actually the day for the
data cleaning I hate to say it but it's
true
yep and that's really important because
like the quality of your data has a huge
impact on how good you are at your job
like down like that just propagates all
the way downstream so a lot of my time
is also spent thinking about whether the
data that I have is appropriate for the
questions that I'm trying to answer with
it whether like the representation I
picked is a good one you know trying out
new features that sort of thing you
spent a lot of time that way and then
for a lot of it depends a little bit on
the case but for some data scientists
it's a lot of figuring out just sort of
one-off
answers to questions and so that might
be sort of feel a little bit more
exploratory and you're working in like a
notebook and it's a new question every
day for other data scientists they're
more like software engineers so once you
figure out how to solve a problem
your task is figuring out how to solve
it you know repeatedly at very high
scale you need to make sure that the
results that you're getting are
understandable by people who aren't
technical and so
that can be a lot of work as well is
like figuring out how to approach it as
a software engineering problem in
addition to a statistics problem do you
sometimes go beyond the the data then
you have store in your computer and take
into account events that are happening
in the news or information that you can
gather from somewhere else oh that's an
interesting question I mean so I'm
always paying attention so that the type
of work that I do in particular for data
science deals with a lot of like person
level data and so thinking about what's
going on in the world and how people are
interacting with technology and you know
how they might be responding to events
in the world like that can that can be
pretty important so yeah thinking about
if if we want to set up a way to get
some data from Twitter for example might
be a way that I spend some time um yeah
and I think a lot of a lot of the work
is also because this is a field that's
changing so quickly and there's a new
thing coming out every day a lot of my
job is also as much as possible trying
to keep up with that firehose and make
sure you know there's no way you can
learn everything but trying to make sure
that it at least you know kind of where
the field is heading and making sure
that you don't get too far behind what
do you use to keep yourself up to date
what are some of the resources now that
you brought it obviously do you have
anything other than Udacity of course
yeah sure well I have my own podcast so
I I'm a fan of that so oh what's your
podcast oh it's called linear
digressions I talk about machine
learning for 20 minutes every week oh
that's awesome
yeah it'll include this in the show
notes and that's actually I mean this is
this doesn't generalize that well to
like you know I you have to have a
podcast to do this so it you know that
takes a lot of work but that's actually
been for me personally the way that I've
learned a ton because every week I have
to come up with something to talk about
and that really forces you to stop and
think about you know you're like oh no
what am I going to talk about this week
and I think also participating in like
the larger data science communicate
community so for some people this might
mean
using Twitter and following data
scientists on Twitter sometimes this
means you know if you are fortunate
enough to work in a company where you
have a lot of colleagues who are really
paying attention to this stuff using
them as resources participating in the
open-source community I find that
there's a lot of noise around data
science and machine learning and so
trying to figure out it's not that hard
to find people talking about this it can
be harder to find really good
high-quality sources so whenever you
find sort of like smart people who are
talking about it and trying to
understand it that can be a really good
place to kind of plant your flag and
listen in on those conversations and
contribute to them too so that can take
a lot of forms but you know just trying
to find those those little pockets of
the community where good work is being
done and and following along has been
really beneficial to me Katie thank you
for coming on the show it was great
talking to you today oh it was
absolutely my pleasure thank you for
such wonderful conversation for software
engineering radio this was Diana Salinas
thank you for listening thanks for
listening to se radio an educational
program brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine for more information
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at SE -
radioman to provide feedback you can
write comments on each episode on the
website or write a review on itunes
mention a message us on Twitter at se
radio or search for the software
engineering radio group on Lane
Plus or Facebook you can also email us a
team at SC - radio net this and all
other episodes of SU radio is licensed
under the Creative Commons 2.5 license
thanks again for your support
[Music]
you